<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>We&#39;ll burn that bridge when we get to it on We&#39;ll burn that bridge when we get to it </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://axylos.github.io/blog/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 15:23:49 EDT</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitching about Load ruined Metallica</title>
      <link>https://axylos.github.io/blog/post/metallica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 15:23:49 EDT</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://axylos.github.io/blog/post/metallica/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have only yourself to blame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the thoughts that keep me awake at night, concerns about flogging a &lt;em&gt;very dead&lt;/em&gt; horse be damned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjEt-LFws3TAhWE6CYKHaAZAgwQFggnMAA&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.blabbermouth.net%2Fnews%2Fdream-theater-drummer-bob-rock-ruined-metallica%2F&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGFJ2rXdHykDCbqXPwY8twWNEvbsQ&amp;amp;sig2=Yj2A6SfxbXd1_h0qu190-w&amp;amp;cad=rja&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For those who aren&amp;rsquo;t quite up to speed on the recent unpleasantness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or you can also read up on it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtv.com/news/1592476/metallica-compare-hands-off-producer-rick-rubin-to-longtime-hand-holder-bob-rock/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=4&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjEt-LFws3TAhWE6CYKHaAZAgwQFgg6MAM&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Foffthetracks.co.nz%2Fclassic-albums-i-cant-ever-listen-to-again-9-metallica-metallica%2F&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNG744YuXeYcljPkfE-PQhPR&amp;amp;sig2=_XOXU4Om_KdbUzRcj7_PaA&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;over here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=bob+rock+ruined+metallica&amp;amp;rlz=1C5CHFA_enUS570US571&amp;amp;oq=bob+rock+ruined+metallica&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j0l5.2867j0j7&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;or just google it I&amp;rsquo;m tired of posting links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Prior to all of that Metallica produced some very good music, and then by the mid to late 90&amp;rsquo;s even the most forgiving had to admit all hope was lost.&lt;br /&gt;
What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt; They flirted with the commercial dark side while coming down off an extended mourning period and then tried to explore musically. No one had any patience for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-band-could-have-moved-on-after-cliff-burton-s-death&#34;&gt;The band could have moved on after Cliff Burton&amp;rsquo;s death&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under normal circumstances,
 demanding that a group of mid-20-somethings cope with the loss of a close friend,
 find his replacement,
 and then record,
 release, and tour to support a new album within a two year time period would be considered cruel, and it&amp;rsquo;s a testament to all involved that the music was still very good.
 &amp;ndash;&lt;em&gt;thank god given how merciless the backlash would prove to be when Metallica began to lose their way&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;
 Destructive alcohol and hard drug abuse notwithstanding, the resilience displayed by the surviving bandmates and a terrified replacement was quite admirable.&lt;br /&gt;
 Sure, lyrical themes became uncharacteristically politically angsty, Jason Newsted&amp;rsquo;s bass volume was near subliminal, and everyone struggled with unhealthy self-medication,
 but some otherworldy alchemy of artistic focus, manic abandonment to one&amp;rsquo;s work, and quite plausibly overwhelming pressure kept things together.
 As should now be obvious, that kind of pace is unsustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-s-not-all-bob-rock-s-fault&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not all Bob Rock&amp;rsquo;s fault&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of it &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; is.&lt;br /&gt;
While regrettable, the Black Album was not a watershed moment.&lt;br /&gt;
Following the emotional chaos of &lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;And Justice for All&lt;/em&gt;, something uncannily resembling an attempt to grow up appeared out of the shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more &amp;ldquo;professional&amp;rdquo; producer was brought in with the stated purpose of widening the band&amp;rsquo;s appeal and furthering their development, which is not necessarily a bad thing, especicially
for a group of people who consciously or not were probably looking to settle down, i.e., get married/start families, and function somewhat normally.  Aside from that, not much more needs to be said,
  except for the fact that there were multiple divorces duing the following two year world tour, a near death pyrotechnic accident, and Axl Rose was an asshole.
  It&amp;rsquo;s safe to say that if there had been a sincere attempt to find a new balance, unforeseen developments made for a challenging work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; music was cramped and overly self-aware; the second chapter of healing didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be going so hot; touring for that long really does take its toll;
a skateboard injury permanently impaired Kirk Hammet&amp;rsquo;s right hand leading to a lot of wah-wah;
James Hetfield learned what vocal chord damage feels like; and the USSR fell.&lt;br /&gt;
There were hushed whispers of a sellout, but nothing beyond what&amp;rsquo;s typical for an act that&amp;rsquo;s been so prolific and long-lasting.
So they took a few years off before doing anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;selling-out-is-a-lot-easier-when-the-entire-fanbase-asks-for-it&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Selling Out&amp;rdquo; is a lot easier when the entire fanbase asks for it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then this shit happened&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn.ustatik.com/article/draft/12793_MpmaGDF2l8EGsa7x_1483.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;friends don&#39;t let friends get haircuts&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-extended-break the now-30-something musicians toned down the furiously palm-muted running lines and horse growls in favor of dark, bluesy crooning and the country-inspired bending lick here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting effect is eerily bleak and unsettling.
Lyrically, the songs became more vulnerable and monstrously honest, with the past decade of unresolved and corrosive turbulence on full display. The aggressive rage of the 80&amp;rsquo;s replaced
by a more resigned and fearful gloom akin to the nihilistic, uneasy atmosphere of Alice in Chains.  Still, if viewed from the right angle, it could almost seem like a more mature and healthy approach to both
 music and coping was beginning to take root.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter in the slightest when you&amp;rsquo;re a Metallica fan; the real burning issue of the time was that they all got haircuts and unapologetically plastered a photo with the new look
on the back of &lt;em&gt;Load&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Having forsaken an unspoken social code and their own artistic integrity,
Metallica inflicted this upon the world for the low, low 90&amp;rsquo;s cartel prices
of around $20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/54da7ffbe4b06c67da90bea3/t/57523eed746fb9da8815ecf8/1465007859211/&#34; alt=&#34;load cover&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the horror&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that really sucks.&lt;br /&gt;
What could we expect from mere mortals who face years of accusations that they had forgotten their roots and sold out?&lt;br /&gt;
Empirically, it&amp;rsquo;s safe to conclude that said mere mortals
give the fuck up and try everything from aping a crude popular aesthetic that is several generations removed, to forcing
some very irritated professional classical musicians to play awkward arrangements of 80&amp;rsquo;s metal, or making a last ditch
attempt to give fans the very thing they were asking for &lt;em&gt;and probably deserved&lt;/em&gt;, viz., a limpid echo of their work from 20 years prior, 8
minute track lengths and all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn&amp;rsquo;t have to be this way.  Metallica could have aged gracefully.  While noticeably different, it&amp;rsquo;s conceivable that the band
would have produced a line of work broadly continuous with rest of their career, taking a decidedly more sober and vulnerable
gaze into the very real nightmares that provided the creative catalysts for the earlier music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, critics, fans, and anyone else unfortunate enough to have been exposed to the last few albums has been greeted with
sadly uncertain and directionless art.  Not unlike the manuscripts and legacy of Anton Bruckner, a man so harried and
filled with doubts from incessant and unrequested artistic suggestions from friends and colleagures, he got his own
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Bruckner#The_Bruckner_Problem&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;eponymous academic problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s not do this again.  Any of it.  Don&amp;rsquo;t shit on artists for failing to please all the time every time;
don&amp;rsquo;t forget that celebrities are people too; don&amp;rsquo;t name your album &amp;ldquo;Deah Magnetic&amp;rdquo;; and most importantly,
don&amp;rsquo;t overly format your first attempt at a markdown blog post so liberally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tia,&lt;br /&gt;
Drake&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
